<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2005-90">
  <num>2005-90</num>
  <heading>Tribal Membership Board and Membership Code</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2005-12-07</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2005-12-07</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2005-90.pdf">Res. No. 2005-90</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the St. Regis Mohawk Tribal Council is the duly recognized governing body of the St. Regis Mohawk Tribe and is responsible for the health, safety, education and welfare of all community members; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>there has been discrepancy regarding which Membership Code is the official Code for the St. Regis Mohawk Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>on April 19, 1986 the Membership Board developed a Membership Code which was voted on in a referendum. It passed by two votes (93/91). This Code would have limited enrollment to those who were at least 50% Mohawk; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>this Membership Code was never implemented, and a second draft of the Membership Code was presented to the Tribal Clerk for implementation (attached and marked "E");</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council directs that the 25% blood quantum Membership Code marked "E" will be followed until a decision to the contrary or referendum or Tribal Council Resolution is passed adopting a Code that supercedes this Code; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>according to Membership Code "E" any questions regarding enrollment eligibility are to be appealed to the "Membership Court" and not the Membership Board. The Membership Court, according to any version of the Membership Code, is comprised of the three (3) Sub Chiefs; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>the St. Regis Mohawk Tribal Council hereby rescinds TCR # 2003-203 appointing the current Membership Board members; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>the St. Regis Mohawk Tribal Chiefs hereby appoint the three Sub-Chiefs, namely, Emily Lauzon, Ronald LaFrance, Jr., and Donald D. Thompson, Sr., as the Membership Court effective December 7, 2005.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>THE SAINT REGIS MOHAWK TRIBAL COUNCIL</text>
    <text>
      <table class="layout-table">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>_____________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">_____________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">_____________________</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Barbara A. Lazore, Chiefm</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">James W. Ransom, Chief</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">Lorraine M. White, Chief</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <em>CERTIFICATION</em>
      </strong>
      <em>; This is to certify that the above resolution was duly passed by the St. Regis Mohawk Tribal Council pursuant to the authority vested therein.</em>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table class="layout-table">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>___________________________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-4">December 07/05</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Patricia Thomas, Tribal Clerk</td>
            <td class="text-indent-4">Date</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
