<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Code of Law">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>5</num>
  <heading>Environment</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.03</num>
    <heading>Solid Waste Management Code</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.010</num>
      <heading/>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>INTRODUCTION</strong>
        </text>
        <text>It is the tradition of the Mohawk People to look generations forward in planning. It is with this foresight that the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Solid Waste Management Code ("Code") is intended.</text>
        <text>Solid waste disposal practices need to be maintained in good harmony with Mother Earth since these practices will have an effect on the future generations inheriting this land. Adherence to <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> will ensure that best practices for solid waste management are maintained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>AUTHORITY</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe ("Tribe" or "SRMT") has the inherent authority to manage and regulate the storage, collection, transportation, handling, treatment and disposal of solid waste in a manner which best protects Mother Earth, her natural resources, and the health, welfare, and economic security of this generation of Mohawk People and the generations to follow.</text>
        <text>The Tribe retains the inherent sovereign power to exercise civil authority and jurisdiction over the conduct of both Tribal and non-Tribal members on all lands within the Saint Regis Mohawk Indian Reservation ("Reservation"). These civil actions will be taken when necessary to maintain the environment, natural resources, public health, safety, welfare, political integrity and economic security of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>PURPOSE</strong>
        </text>
        <text><cite path="|5.03">This chapter</cite> does not allow for the improper disposal of any Solid Waste on the Reservation. Improper disposal or creating an Open Dump of any Solid Waste materials or recyclables, whether on the side of the road, in the Community Recycling Depot, or anywhere that they should not be disposed of, will be considered a violation of the Code. Disposal of such Solid Waste or creating an Open Dump site is different than someone who litters as outlined in the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Traffic Code Section III(5)(f) (TCR 2018-09 or as amended).</text>
        <text>It is the intent of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> to create a comprehensive integrated waste management policy that requires all solid waste to be disposed of properly at management facilities on and off the Reservation. <cite path="|5.03">This chapter</cite> encourages Mohawk People to reduce, recycle and reuse those materials that do not belong in the waste stream. Education of the community through diverse media has been a continuing process, aimed at eliminating the poor solid waste disposal practices of the past.</text>
        <text>The Code intends to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Protect the health and safety of Tribal members and all other persons within the Reservation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Protect the cultural, social and economic stability of residential, agricultural, commercial, industrial, forest, riparian, and environmentally sensitive lands within the Reservation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Protect the historical and cultural values and traditions of the Tribe, Mohawk land as a permanent Tribal homeland, and maintain its aboriginal character;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Prevent solid waste pollution, including contamination of the Tribe's groundwater, surface waters, drinking water supplies, and all other natural resources;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Prevent the deterioration of the environment, standard of living, quality of life, welfare and well-being of all persons within the Reservation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Provide and promote Tribal waste management efficiency and services within the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.020</num>
      <heading/>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>DEFINITIONS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided or the context requires another definition, the definitions set forth in <cite path="|5.03.020|(a)">Section 5.03.020(a)</cite> shall apply to the terms used throughout <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Closure</u>
          </text>
          <text>The termination of the receiving, handling, recycling, treatment, composting, or disposal of solid wastes at a management facility. It shall include all operations necessary to prepare the management facility for post-closure maintenance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Conditionally Exempt Small Quantity Generators</u>
          </text>
          <text>Facilities that produce less than 100 kg (220.5 lbs.) of hazardous waste, or less than 1 kg (2.205 lbs.) of acutely hazardous waste per calendar month.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Collection</u>
          </text>
          <text>The act of collecting solid wastes by a SRMT permitted Hauler.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Construction</u>
          </text>
          <text>The erection or building of new structures and the acquisition, replacement, expansion, remodeling, alteration, modernization, or extension of existing structures.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Director</u>
          </text>
          <text>The Director (person in charge) of the Tribe's Environment Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Disposal</u>
          </text>
          <text>The discharge, deposit, injection, dumping, spilling, leaking, or placing of any solid waste into or on any land or water so that such solid waste or any constituent thereof may enter the environment or be emitted into the air, or discharged into any waters, including surface waters or ground waters.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Environment Division</u>
          </text>
          <text>The Division of the Tribe whose mission is to preserve, protect, restore, and enhance the community of Akwesasne for the present and future generations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Farm</u>
          </text>
          <text>A facility that raises or harvests any agricultural or horticultural commodity through the cultivation of the soil, aquaculture product or the raising, shearing, feeding, caring for, training or management of livestock, bee, poultry, fur bearing animals, fish, domestic animals or wildlife.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Financial Mechanism</u>
          </text>
          <text>A trust fund or other equivalent financial arrangement acceptable to the Environment Division to provide the financial assurances required by <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Floodplain</u>
          </text>
          <text>Land that would be inundated with floodwater as a result of the occurrence of a 100-year flood.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Groundwater</u>
          </text>
          <text>Water below the land surface in a zone of saturation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Guidance Document</u>
          </text>
          <text>A document prepared by the Environment Division that supplements criteria under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>. A guidance document may provide specific technical direction regarding the manner in which an owner or operator shall comply with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>. Guidance documents may be referred to or attached as conditions to permits. Such technical direction must either conform to <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, or be more stringent. A guidance document may also provide direction as to how the Director of the Environment Division interprets the Tribe's solid waste permit program, consistent with Tribal laws and <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(13)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Hauler</u>
          </text>
          <text>A person or commercial establishment that is in the business of collecting and transporting solid wastes and who has obtained a Tribal permit from the SRMT's Compliance Department ("Compliance Department").</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(14)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Hazardous Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>A waste that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Because of its quantity, concentration, or physical, chemical, or infectious characteristics, may either cause or significantly contribute to an increase in mortality or serious irreversible or incapacitating illness. It may pose a substantial present or potential hazard to human health, living organisms, or the environment when improperly handled, treated, stored, transported, or disposed of; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Is specifically defined to be hazardous or toxic, including but not limited to any substance, material, smoke, gas, particulate matter, or combination thereof. Materials containing asbestos, petroleum or its byproducts, or Polychlorinated Biphenyls (PCBs); or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Is hazardous, toxic, ignitable, reactive, or corrosive, and that is defined and regulated as such by the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(15)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Household Hazardous Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>Chemical products such as paints, solvents or pesticides generated from normal household activities (e.g. routine house and yard maintenance).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(16)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Industrial Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>A subset of solid wastes, which are generated by manufacturing or industrial processes. Such processes may include, but are not limited to the following: electric power generation; fertilizer/agricultural chemicals; inorganic chemicals; iron and steel manufacturing; leather and leather products; nonferrous metals manufacturing/foundries; organic chemicals; plastics and resins manufacturing; pulp and paper industry; rubber and miscellaneous plastic products; stone, glass, clay and concrete products; textile manufacturing; transportation equipment; and water treatment. The forms of such wastes are exemplified by, but not limited to, liquids such as acids, alkalis, caustics, leachate, petroleum (and its derivatives), and processes or treatment wastewaters; sludges which are semi-solid substances resulting from process or treatment operations or residues from storage or use of liquids; solidified chemicals, paints or pigments; and dredge soil, foundry sand, and the end or by- products of incineration or other forms of combustion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(17)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Infectious/Medical Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>A subset of solid wastes that include but are not limited to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Laboratory wastes, including but not limited to cultures of etiological agents (agents that cause diseases), which pose a substantial threat to health due to their volume and virulence.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Pathological specimens, including but not limited to human or animal tissues, blood elements, excreta, and secretions that contain etiologic agents, and attendant disposable fomites.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Surgical specimens, including but not limited to human or animal parts and tissues removed surgically, or at autopsy, which in the opinion of the attending physician or veterinarian, contain etiologic agents and attendant disposable fomites.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Human dialysis waste materials, including but not limited to arterial lines and dialysate membranes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>Carcasses of animals infected with etiological agents that may present a substantial hazard to public health if improperly managed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>Equipment, instruments, utensils, or any other material that is likely to transmit etiologic agents or presents a significant danger of infection, because it is contaminated with, or may reasonably be expected to be contaminated with, etiologic agents.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(18)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Inherently Waste-like Material</u>
          </text>
          <text>A material, such as dioxin-containing wastes, that is always considered a solid waste because of its intrinsic threat to human health and the environment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(19)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Liquid Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>Waste material that contains free liquid.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(20)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Management Facility</u>
          </text>
          <text>All contiguous land and structures, other appurtenances, and improvements on the land used for the management of solid wastes.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(21)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Municipal Solid Wastes (MSW)</u>
          </text>
          <text>A subset of solid waste that is defined as durable and non-durable goods, containers and packaging, food wastes, yard trimmings, and miscellaneous organic wastes from residential, commercial, and industrial non-process sources.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(22)</num>
          <text>
            <u>MSWLF</u>
          </text>
          <text>Municipal Solid Waste Landfill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(23)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Nuisance</u>
          </text>
          <text>A condition that occurs as a result of the handling, treatment, composting, or disposal of solid waste, which</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>is injurious to human health or is indecent or offensive to the senses and interferes with the comfortable enjoyment of life or property, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Affects an entire community or neighborhood or any considerable number of persons.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(24)</num>
          <text>
            <u>100-Year Flood</u>
          </text>
          <text>A flood that has a 1 in 100 chance of being equaled or exceeded in any one (1) year, and it has an average recurrence interval of one hundred (100) years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(25)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Open Burning</u>
          </text>
          <text>Burning of unwanted materials such as paper, trees, brush, leaves, grass, and other debris where smoke and other emissions are released directly into the air. During open burning, air pollutants do not pass through a chimney or stack</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(26)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Open Dump</u>
          </text>
          <text>Any management facility or site including roadways and ditches on the Reservation where Solid Waste has been disposed of, which is not a sanitary landfill or transfer station authorized under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(27)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Operator</u>
          </text>
          <text>The person(s) responsible for the overall operation of a management facility or part of a management facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(28)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Owner</u>
          </text>
          <text>The person(s) who owns a management facility or part of a management facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(29)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Permit</u>
          </text>
          <text>An authorization and license issued under the authority of the Compliance Department regulating the collection and transportation of MSW and/or solid waste, or regulating the treatment and disposal of MSW and/or solid waste including the construction and/or operation of a management facility.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(30)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Permittee</u>
          </text>
          <text>A person, hauler, or entity who is authorized and permitted by the Compliance Department to collect and transport MSW and/or solid wastes, or to construct or operate a management facility in compliance with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(31)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Permit Documents</u>
          </text>
          <text>Permit applications, drafts and final permits, or other documents that include applicable design and management conditions in accordance with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, and the technical and administrative information used to explain the basis of permit conditions, including applicable guidance documents. The unauthorized disposal of any solid waste into the air, land, surface water or groundwater.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(32)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Person</u>
          </text>
          <text>Any individual, trust, firm, association, partnership, Indian Tribe, tribally chartered corporation, business, or LLC, political subdivision, government agency, industry, public or private corporation, any legal entity or private enterprise. It also includes members of the Tribe, all other non-member Indians, and all non-Indians.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(33)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Pollution</u>
          </text>
          <text>The unauthorized disposal of any solid waste into the air, land, surface of the water or groundwater.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(34)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Post-Closure Maintenance</u>
          </text>
          <text>All activities undertaken at a closed management facility to maintain the integrity of containment features and to monitor compliance with applicable performance standards as required under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(35)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Post-Closure Maintenance Period</u>
          </text>
          <text>A period of at least thirty (30) years after closure of a management facility, or Solid Waste Program, a period which ends only after the operator demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Director of the Environment Division that the solid waste contained in such facility no longer poses any threat to human health and the environment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(36)</num>
          <text>
            <u>RCRA (Resource Conservation and Recovery Act)</u>
          </text>
          <text>An Environmental Protection Agency policy, which regulates the generation, transportation and storage of solid and hazardous waste recovery.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(37)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Recovery</u>
          </text>
          <text>The reclamation of material, byproducts, or energy from solid waste.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(38)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Recycling</u>
          </text>
          <text>The process of separating and collecting solid wastes, their subsequent transformation or remanufacture into usable or marketable products or materials, and the purchase of products made from materials that have already been used in some form.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(39)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Reuse</u>
          </text>
          <text>The process of reusing solid wastes for the same purpose that it was originally designed, or using it for a different purpose.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(40)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Regulated Hazardous Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>In RCRA ยง 1004(5), Congress defined hazardous waste as a solid waste, or combination of solid wastes, which because of its quantity, concentration, or physical, chemical, or infectious characteristics may:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Cause, or significantly contribute to, an increase in mortality or an increase in serious irreversible, or incapacitating reversible, illness; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Pose a substantial present or potential hazard to human health or the environment when improperly treated, stored, transported, or disposed of, or otherwise managed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(41)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Removal</u>
          </text>
          <text>The act of taking solid waste from the place of generation or storage, either by an approved collection agency or by the owner of the solid waste.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(42)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Reservation</u>
          </text>
          <text>Reservation means both the Saint Regis Mohawk Indian Tribe Reservation as established by the 1796 Treaty with the Seven Nations of Canada (7 Stat. 55) and any other lands over which the Tribe exercises jurisdiction now or in the future.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(43)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Rules and Regulations</u>
          </text>
          <text>Any policies promulgated by the Environment Division, and adopted by the Tribal Council, regulating the collection, transportation or disposal of solid waste on the Reservation, which will implement, supplement or regulate any provisions of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(44)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Sanitary Landfill</u>
          </text>
          <text>A disposal facility employing a method of disposing of solid waste on land, without creating nuisances, pollution or hazards to public health or safety, by using methods to confine the solid waste to the smallest practical area, to reduce it to the smallest practical volume, and to cover it with a layer of suitable cover material at specific designated intervals. A MSWLF under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> is a sanitary landfill.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(45)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Sewage Sludge</u>
          </text>
          <text>A subset of solid wastes that includes any residue, excluding grit or screenings, removed from wastewater, whether in a dry, semi-dry, or liquid form.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(46)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Sludge</u>
          </text>
          <text>A sub-set of solid waste that may be solid, semi-solid, or liquid waste generated from a commercial, or industrial wastewater treatment plant, water supply treatment plant, or air pollution control facility, exclusive of the treated effluent from a wastewater treatment plant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(47)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Special Wastes</u>
          </text>
          <text>A subset of solid wastes, which is listed in <cite path="|5.03.040|(b)">Section 5.03.040(b)</cite> of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Radioactive wastes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>All regulated hazardous wastes as defined by RCRA.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Infectious biomedical wastes, which includes human tissue or human anatomical remains.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Animals or bedding exposed to infectious agents.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>Bulk quantities of infectious-type wastes which have been in contact with: blood, blood products and body fluids are handled by Indian Health Services (IHS) through a qualified vendor for disposal.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>Any materials containing friable asbestos waste.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(G)</num>
            <text>Sewage or sewage sludge wastes.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(H)</num>
            <text>Bulk liquids of any kind.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(I)</num>
            <text>Polychlorinated Biphenyls (PCBs).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(J)</num>
            <text>Explosives.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(K)</num>
            <text>Hazardous waste generated from small quantity generators.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(48)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Solid Waste</u>
          </text>
          <text>Any garbage, or refuse, sludge from a residence, business, wastewater treatment plant, water supply treatment plant, or air pollution control facility and other discarded materials, resulting from industrial, commercial mining, or agricultural operations, and from community activities, businesses or residences. It includes any discarded or abandoned materials. It can be solid, liquid, semi-solid or containerized gaseous material.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(49)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Solid Waste Transfer Station (SWTS) or Transfer Station</u>
          </text>
          <text>A publicly or privately-owned facility or site that receives solid waste as for the purpose of sorting, recycling, compacting, recovering, and transferring solid waste. A SWTS unit may be a new unit, an existing unit or a lateral expansion. A lateral expansion is the horizontal expansion of an existing unit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(50)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Source Reduction</u>
          </text>
          <text>The design, manufacture, and use of products in a way that reduces the quantity and toxicity of waste produced when the products reach the end of their useful lives; i.e. waste prevention.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(51)</num>
          <text>
            <u>SWDA (The Solid Waste Disposal Act)</u>
          </text>
          <text>Solid Waste Disposal Act of 1965, set national goals for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Protecting human health and the environment from the potential hazards of waste disposal.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Conserving energy and natural resources.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Reducing the amount of waste generated.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Ensuring that wastes are managed in an environmentally-sound manner. https://www.epa.gov/history</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(52)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Treatment</u>
          </text>
          <text>When used in connection with hazardous waste, is any method, technique, or process, including neutralization, designed to change the physical, chemical, or biological character or composition of any hazardous waste so as to neutralize such waste or so as to render such waste non-hazardous, safer for transport, amendable for recovery, amendable for storage, or reduced in volume. Such term includes any activity or processing designed to change the physical form or chemical composition of hazardous waste so as to render it non-hazardous.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(53)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Tribe's Solid Waste Disposal Program</u>
          </text>
          <text>All the authorities, activities and procedures under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, the Tribe's Solid Waste Management Plan, and any other Tribal laws or regulations that comprise the Tribe's system of permits, and prior approval and conditions for regulating the collection, handling, transportation, and disposal, treatment and storage of solid waste, including all of the location, operation, design, groundwater monitoring, corrective action, closure, post-closure and financial assurance requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(54)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Tribe's Solid Waste Management Plan and Regulations</u>
          </text>
          <text>The formulation of Tribal policies for all solid waste collection, handling, transportation, disposal, treatment, storage, source reduction, reusing, recycling and resource conservation on the Reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(55)</num>
          <text>
            <u>Vector</u>
          </text>
          <text>Any insect, arthropod, rodent, or other animal capable of transmitting a pathogen from one organism to another, or of disrupting the normal enjoyment of life by adversely affecting the public health and well-being.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.030</num>
      <heading>Designation of Authority</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>ENVIRONMENT DIVISION AND COMPLIANCE DEPARTMENT</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The Tribe respects the thoughts and teachings of the Mohawk People and is entrusted to protect the land, air, water, vegetation and animal life for the next seven generations. To accomplish this mission as it relates to solid waste management, the Tribe hereby appoints the Environment Division as the lead Tribal agency to ensure the proper management of solid wastes while the Tribe's Compliance Department is delegated the authority to issue permits and maintain compliance with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>. The Environment Division and the Compliance Department shall each have the powers, duties, and responsibilities as provided herein.</text>
        <text>The Environment Division shall develop and manage the Tribe's comprehensive integrated waste management policy and regulations using both the traditional concept of seven generations and by the duties specifically designated in <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> or as may be assigned from time to time by the Environment Division Director or Tribal Council. The Environment Division shall communicate to the community information regarding the Tribe's comprehensive integrated waste management policy and make reports containing such information as the Tribe approves, excluding any confidential or privileged information.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>Duties of the Environment Division with Respect to Solid Wastes.</heading>
          <text>The Environment Division is entrusted to protect the land, air, water, vegetation and animal life for the future generations from the detrimental effects of improper management of solid waste. To accomplish this task the Environment Division shall perform the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Develop and implement the Tribe's Solid Waste Management Plan. The goal of the Solid Waste Management Plan is to provide guidance to manage solid wastes in a manner that honors the earth, people, plants, animals, and waters, while contributing to the economic and social progress of the community.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Build on the community's inherent respect for the natural world by maintaining and improving the processes and equipment utilized in the management of solid wastes, recyclable and reusable materials. Provide the technical standards and criteria for the collection and transportation of Solid Waste.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Prepare an inventory and location of all open dumping sites in and around the Reservation where solid wastes have been disposed, and a plan to close all such sites.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Encourage community involvement and input in the Tribe's Solid Waste Management Plan;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>Prepare technical reports as may be requested from time to time, including environmental assessments as may be necessary.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>Administer, supervise, monitor, and investigate the collection, transportation, and disposal of Solid Waste on the Reservation in compliance with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, as well as adhere to all laws, rules and regulations, and Guidance Documents promulgated hereunder.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(G)</num>
            <text>Investigate and prepare applications for private, Federal or State grants or funding, and provide financial and technical assistance to implement the Tribe's Solid Waste Management Plan.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(H)</num>
            <text>Maintain and renew permits for the collection and transportation of and for the operation of the Solid Waste Transfer Station.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(I)</num>
            <text>Ensure that proper handling, collection and disposal of regulated Hazardous Waste is done in accordance with <cite path="|5.03.040">Section 5.03.040</cite> of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Duty of the Compliance Department to Investigate Under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite></strong>
          </text>
          <text>Upon receiving a credible complaint by any person, or upon its own initiative, the Environment Division shall request that the Compliance Department perform a thorough investigation of any violations made by any person, Management Facility, or Hauler. The Compliance Department shall prepare a report which will then be submitted to the Environment Division, Tribal Council and General Counsel.</text>
          <text>A credible complaint is a complaint that relates to, but is not limited to, improper disposal methods, unauthorized acceptance of special wastes, inappropriate handling, collection and transportation of solid waste and/or worker safety issues.</text>
          <text>If a complaint is founded then an Enforcement Action pursuant to <cite path="|5.03.060|(c)">Section 5.03.060(c)</cite> may be undertaken. For any complaint that is unfounded a report shall be transmitted to the complainant within thirty (30) days of the investigation's completion.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.040</num>
      <heading>Proper Handling, Collection and Disposal of Solid Wastes</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>INTEGRATED WASTE MANAGEMENT</strong>
        </text>
        <text>An integrated waste management approach shall be used for the management of Solid Wastes. This approach shall promote reducing, reusing, and recycling, followed by disposal.</text>
        <text>The Environment Division may issue rules and regulations for reducing, reusing, and recycling of solid wastes on the Reservation. Proper and safe practices based on industry standards will be developed to increase safety in the recovery phase of these efforts.</text>
        <text>The Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe will abide by restrictions on recyclables at the landfill (County of Franklin Solid Waste "Local Law No. 3".) The following rules apply to this Solid Waste Code for recyclable materials:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All recyclables shall be separated from Municipal Solid Waste</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Designated Recyclables shall not be contaminated with hazardous waste or any other solid waste.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Recyclables will be delivered in a manner to follow these requirements or they may be rejected.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>OPEN DUMPING</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The open dumping of Solid Wastes on the Reservation is disrespectful and does irreparable damage to the land and the environment. Much of this waste can last longer than seven generations and can affect even more generations through contamination of: soil, groundwater, and surface waters. Proper disposal of these materials can be accomplished through the utilization of Management Facilities, Haulers and/or taken directly off reservation to permitted disposal areas.</text>
        <text>It is a violation of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> for anyone or business to operate an Open Dump site. If there is an allegation of an Open Dump site it shall be investigated. The Open Dump site shall immediately cease to operate and violator will be subject to enforcement actions as outlined in <cite path="|5.03.060|(c)">Section 5.03.060(c)</cite>. if the matter was not resolved under <cite path="|5.03.030|(a)|(2)">Section 5.03.030(a)(2)</cite>.</text>
        <text>It is a violation of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> to dump, scatter or place any solid wastes anywhere except at a duly authorized and designated solid waste transfer station or landfill. Any written or verbal allegation of open dumping shall be forwarded to the Compliance Department to investigate. If the alleged violator's conduct does not cease after the Compliance Department has undertaken efforts to seek cooperation to stop the offending behavior, it may then determine whether to refer the matter to Tribal Police or the Environment Division for further enforcement action.</text>
        <text>If there are further enforcement actions and the matter is brought to the Tribal Court, it shall be dealt with according to <cite path="|5.03.060|(d)">Section 5.03.060(d)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>BURNING OF SOLID WASTE</strong>
        </text>
        <text>Any burning of Solid Wastes will be done in accordance with the open burn regulations established by the Environment Division's Clean Air Program (see TCR 2002-59 or as amended)</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>HOUSEHOLD HAZARDOUS WASTES</strong>
        </text>
        <text>On specified days during the calendar year, certain Household Hazardous Wastes will be accepted at specific drop off areas on the Reservation for proper disposal. Only on those days and at those locations will a limited number of prohibited special wastes be accepted. The wastes allowed will be listed and announced thirty (30) calendar days prior to the collection date by the Director of the Environment Division.</text>
        <text>All items to be included in the Household Hazardous Waste collection will be compiled on a list by the Director of the Environment Division. The permitted items will be announced in a locally circulated newspaper, the Tribe's website, social media and radio for at least three (3) consecutive weeks prior to collection activities. Disposal methods and containers will follow recognized standards established by United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) and Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA). Rules and regulations adopted by the Environment Division may be used if those methods specified meet or exceed the minimum standards established by USEPA and OSHA.</text>
        <text>If the Director or any employee involved with the collection of Household Hazardous Waste is in doubt regarding the safe handling of a product, then such product will be returned to the individual who transported it to the collection point.</text>
        <text>Collection of Household Hazardous Waste will occur based solely on the availability of funding. If the Environment Division deems that regularly scheduled collections are necessary in its discretion, under rules and regulations to be adopted by the Environment Division, then the necessary steps and procedures will be taken to assure regularly scheduled collections.</text>
        <text>Disposing of Household Hazardous Wastes except as outlined above at a Management Facility located on the Reservation is a violation of the Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>SPECIAL WASTES</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The Environment Division may prohibit the disposal of other Solid Wastes at Management Facilities on the Reservation, as it deems necessary, under rules and regulations to be adopted by the Environment Division. The Environment Division shall issue rules and regulations governing the disposal or prohibition of disposal of other Solid Wastes not listed herein, including but not limited to, ashes and powders, and mineral wastes and soils. The Environment Division shall develop rules and regulations for special wastes, which require special handling, treatment and disposal.</text>
        <text>Tribal Departments or agencies, private enterprises, Haulers or any other person are prohibited from disposing of the following Special Wastes at any management facility located within the Reservation.</text>
        <text>Only Haulers who follow applicable Tribal, Federal and State laws and regulations shall collect and transport Special Waste within the Reservation and from the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.050</num>
      <heading>Permit Requirements for Solid Waste Management Activities</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>GENERAL PERMIT REQUIREMENTS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>Tribal departments or agencies, private enterprises, haulers, or any other persons are required to obtain a permit from the Tribe's Compliance Department to collect and/or transport Solid Waste, or to construct or operate a management facility. Any Permittee shall be required to comply with <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, any rule or regulation promulgated thereunder, all Tribal Environmental standards and criteria, all relevant guidance documents, all permit conditions, all orders issued by the Tribe's Compliance Department and applicable Tribal laws.</text>
        <text>No Tribal department or agency, private enterprise, hauler, or person may collect or transport Solid Wastes, or operate a Management Facility within the Reservation without first having obtained from the Environment Division either (1) a solid waste collection and transportation permit; or (2) a solid waste facility construction and/or operation permit.</text>
        <text>In order to provide for Tribal health and safety and to facilitate the conservation of vital Tribal resources, each person living on the Reservation or Tribal business shall provide for the removal of Solid Wastes and recyclables from his/her property on which it is generated either through a service provided by the Tribe or Hauler or by direct haul to a permitted Management Facility approved by the Tribe that is located on the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>PERMITS FOR THE CONSTRUCTION AND OPERATION OF A MANAGEMENT FACILITY</strong>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Management Facility</strong>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <heading>Public Hearing.</heading>
            <text>No Management Facility permit shall be issued unless there has been a public hearing conducted by the Environment Division and Compliance Department at which the applicant and all interested persons shall have an opportunity to present relevant evidence and be heard on whether the application should be granted, or whether there are any special conditions which should be included in such permit. No application may be submitted until a business permit has been granted and an environmental assessment review has been conducted, as well as any other necessary permits are obtained.</text>
            <text>All applications for a solid waste construction and/or operation facility permit, including all documentation required for such permit, shall be available for public review and inspection at least thirty (30) calendar days in advance of the hearing. The Environment Division shall publish a notice of such public hearing on each application at least ten (10) calendar days in advance of the hearing in the locally circulated newspaper. The Environment Division also shall post notice of the public hearing near the proposed permanent site for a management facility, but viewable to the public, at least thirty (30) calendar days in advance of the hearing. The Environment Division may designate issues it deems most relevant in the public notice. Such public hearings shall be recorded.</text>
            <text>The Environment Division also may consider, in consultation with the Compliance Department, certain issues that are raised at the hearing. For any issue, which the Environment Division deems contentious it may decide to address them and provide an analysis of alternatives.</text>
            <text>The information in every application for a Management Facility must include the following information so as to allow the Environment Division in consultation with the Compliance Department to fulfill its responsibilities under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> by:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>having details sufficient to determine how the facility will be constructed, operated, and closed and how it will be monitored and maintained after closure;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>provide sufficient detail to ascertain the environmental impact of the proposed project; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>provide sufficient detail to demonstrate that the design, construction, operation, closure, and post closure monitoring and maintenance of the facility is capable of complying with the applicable requirements of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Unless otherwise specified in <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, the plans and drawings for all Solid Waste Management Facilities must be submitted using the following format:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>the sheet size with title blocks must be 32 by 34 inches or 24 by 26 inches;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>the cover sheet must include the project title, applicant's name, sheet index, legend of symbols, and the engineer's name, address, signature, date of signature and seal;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>the plans relating to the project to its environmental setting must include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>a regional plan or map (having a minimum scale of 1:62,500)</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(II)</num>
                <text>a vicinity plan or map (having a minimum scale of 1:24,000); and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(III)</num>
                <text>an overall site plan (having a minimum scale of 1:2,400 with a five feet minimum contour interval);</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>site plans must contain the location of all property boundaries certified by an individual licensed to practice land surveying in the State of New York;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>the engineering reports for all Solid Waste Management Facilities must:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>contain a cover sheet stating the project title and location, applicant's name, and the engineer's name, address, signature, date of signature and seal;</text>
                <para>
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <text>have its text printed on 8-1/2 x 11-inch pages (paginated consecutively);</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <text>contain a table of contents or index describing the body of the report and the appendices;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <text>include a body of report; and</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <text>include all appendices.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Transfer Stations</strong>
          </text>
          <text>In addition to sections 5.1 &amp; 5.2.1, Transfer Stations receiving less than 50,000 cubic yards or 12,500 tons of Solid Waste annually, must meet the following additional conditions:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Only MSW (and recyclables) are accepted at the facility;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A maximum of 1,000 yards or 250 tons of MSW are located on-site at any given time;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>All putrescible MSW (organic matter capable of being decomposed by microorganisms) is removed from the transfer station within seven (7) days of receipt, unless prior written approval is received from the Environment Division;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>The facility operates only between the hours of sunrise and sunset, or when an attendant is on duty;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>The facility is developed, operated and maintained in a safe, nuisance-free manner; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(F)</num>
            <text>The facility complies with the applicable operational requirements of <cite path="|5.03.040">Section 5.03.040</cite> of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Operational Requirements for Transfer Stations</strong>
          </text>
          <text>All Solid Waste Transfer Stations must comply with the following operational requirements:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text><u>Acceptable waste</u>. Only MSW shall be accepted at the facility. No industrial wastes, special wastes, or construction and demolition debris shall be accepted unless specifically approved by the Environment Division.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text><u>Ultimate disposal of waste</u>. All Solid Waste passing through the Transfer Station must be ultimately treated or disposed of at a facility authorized by the Environment Division if it is located within the Reservation, or by the appropriate governmental agency or agencies if in other states, territories, or nations. In the case of transfer stations at which Solid Waste is intended to be placed on vessels, no Solid Waste shall be placed on a vessel not owned or operated by a City whose population exceeds one million, without having first received written approval from the Environment Division. That approval shall be granted if the operator of the facility submits to the Environment Division the following:</text>
            <text>
              <ul proof="needed">
                <li>a certified copy of each permit or other authorization pertaining to the operation of the treatment or disposal facility to which the Solid Waste will be brought, issued by each governmental entity having jurisdiction over that facility; and,</li>
                <li>original letters from each jurisdiction through which that Solid Waste will pass, and from each jurisdiction in which that Solid Waste will be treated or disposed of, stating that the governmental entity does not object to the Solid Waste being transported through or treated or disposed of within its jurisdiction.</li>
              </ul>
            </text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>PERMITS FOR THE COLLECTION AND TRANSPORTATION OF SOLID WASTE BY HAULERS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>As a condition for the issuance of a Solid Waste collection and transportation permit, the Tribe's Compliance Department shall require every vehicle operated by the Hauler to be conspicuously marked to identify it. Every vehicle shall be marked with the trade name of the Hauler, and the number of the transportation permit issued pursuant to this Section. Every vehicle and driver must be licensed and must comply with all safety and insurance requirements of the state or province from which he/she is licensed.</text>
        <text>After placement of Solid Wastes and recyclable materials at the roadside or other designated area approved by the Tribe for collection, such Solid Wastes and recyclable material shall be delivered to the SRMT Transfer Station located at 179 County Route 43, Fort Covington NY. In certain situations, the Hauler may be granted permission to <strong>by-pass</strong> the SRMT Transfer Station and deliver Solid Waste directly to the Franklin County Landfill. The Hauler must first provide enough historical data to establish a monthly average tonnage of Solid Waste being transported from the Reservation to the landfill. The Hauler will be charged a "Regional Fee". Regional Fees and "Transfer Station Price List" can be found on the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe's webpage (https://www.srmt-nsn.gov/).</text>
        <text>As a condition for the issuance of a Solid Waste collection and transportation permit, a Hauler agrees to make an annual report by December 1 of each year, to the Tribe's Compliance Department, indicating the number and type of installations emptied or cleaned, the quantity of Solid Wastes disposed of, the place and manner in which such Solid Wastes were finally disposed, quantity and types of recyclables collected, and such other information as the Compliance Department may require. A renewal application may be denied by the Compliance Department for failure of the Permittee or Hauler to properly and timely file an annual report.</text>
        <text>The Compliance Department on a calendar basis must renew solid waste permits for the collection and transportation annually. The Environment Division shall adopt rules and regulations for Solid Waste collection and transportation on the Reservation in consultation with the Compliance Department, including the operation of management facilities, and may impose whatever conditions it deems reasonably necessary to protect the environment, and the health, safety and welfare of the Tribe and its members before issuing any permit under this Section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>COMPLIANCE MONITORING</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The Environment Division and/or the Compliance Department shall have the right to request any and all information from any Permittee or Hauler under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, including but not limited to records and technical reports or studies, whether contained in the Permittee's or Hauler's operating record or not, which may be relevant to determine whether a Permittee or Hauler is in compliance with all Tribal Solid Waste requirements, including but not limited to <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, any condition contained in a permit, any rules or regulations promulgated under <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, any guidance documents, any orders issued pursuant to <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, or any Tribal environmental laws. Failure by a Permittee or Hauler to provide the requested information may result in the revocation of his/her permit.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.060</num>
      <heading>Public Involvement and Enforcement</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>PUBLIC PARTICIPATION AND HEARINGS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>The Environment Division may allow for public participation and hold one (1) or more informal public hearings, for the following matters prior to taking any formal action:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The approval of any site location for a new Management Facility;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The issuance of any permits for the construction and/or operation of a Management Facility; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Any other matters which the Environment Division deems appropriate for public participation and review.</text>
          <text>The Environment Division shall schedule such hearings at a convenient location, and give reasonable advance notice of the date, time and subject matter(s) of such hearing, by publication in the newspaper most widely circulated on the Reservation. Thirty (30) calendar days' advance notice is required for the issuance of any management facility permits. There shall be a reasonable opportunity for anyone to comment at such hearings, and to present any relevant information.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>ACTIONS ON PUBLIC COMPLAINTS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>If any department of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, including the Environment Division, receives a credible complaint concerning any person, business, Management Facility owner/operator, or Hauler, giving reasonable grounds that <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>, or any of its rules or regulations, permits conditions, environmental standards, or guidance document, has or is being violated it will forward it to the Tribe's Compliance Department to investigate the matter in accordance with <cite path="|5.03.030|(a)|(2)">Section 5.03.030(a)(2)</cite> of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>ENFORCEMENT ACTIONS</strong>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>Enforcement Policy:</heading>
          <text>While it is the Tribe's policy to encourage informal, practical, result- oriented resolutions of any environmental occurrence it must still prevent damage to the Reservation's resources or prevent harm to the health, safety or welfare of the Reservation's population. It is also the Tribe's policy, consistent with the principles of due process, to provide effective procedures for enforcement. Therefore, after the Compliance Department has finalized its investigation pursuant to <cite path="|5.03.030|(a)|(2)">Section 5.03.030(a)(2)</cite> of a credible complaint it shall forward its findings to the Environment Division, Tribal Council and General Counsel for review and plans of action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <heading>Corrective Action Plan:</heading>
          <text>After receiving the Compliance Department's report, the Environment Division shall review it. After this initial review, the Environment Division may along with the Compliance Department contact the Tribal Member or Tribal Member business causing the environmental concern to devise a corrective action plan to remedy the situation. Environmental concerns can include, but are not limited to, any solid waste regulation or permit condition.</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Member or Tribal Member business agree to a corrective action plan or to cease the offending activity then the Environment Division shall monitor to ensure the corrective action plan is followed or the offending activity is suspended. If the Tribal Member or Tribal Member business fails to follow through on the corrective action plan or cease the activity or refuses to agree to a corrective action plan then the matter shall be referred for further enforcement measures as outlined in <cite path="|5.03.060|(c)|(3)">Section 5.03.060(c)(3)</cite> and <cite path="|5.03.060|(d)">Section 5.03.060(d)</cite>.</text>
          <text>If the corrective action plan is followed or the activity is suspended then the Compliance Department shall conduct a follow-up investigation with a report submitted to the Environment Division, Tribal Council and General Counsel. If the environmental concern is resolved to the Compliance Department and Environment Division's satisfaction then the matter shall be closed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <heading>Cease and Desist Order:</heading>
          <text>If efforts under <cite path="|5.03.060|(c)|(2)">Section 5.03.060(c)(2)</cite> fail then the Tribe's Compliance Department shall serve a Cease and Desist Order on the alleged violator. The failure to comply with a Cease and Desist Order shall constitute a violation of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite></text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>TRIBAL COURT AND HEARINGS ON VIOLATIONS</strong>
        </text>
        <text>
          <strong>Wherever rules are not outlined herein the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe's Rules of Civil Procedure along with the Rules of Evidence shall govern.</strong>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>Complaint.</heading>
          <text>If an alleged violator fails to comply with a Cease and Desist Order from <cite path="|5.03.060|(c)|(3)">Section 5.03.060(c)(3)</cite>. then the Compliance Department shall request General Counsel to file a complaint in Tribal Court. The complaint shall provide notice to the alleged violator of the violation(s) and any other environmental concerns. The Compliance Department shall provide a Summons and arrange for service upon the alleged violator to appear before the Tribal Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <heading>Hearings.</heading>
          <text>On the return date, the Environment Division shall present its documentary proof to the Court and/or present witnesses regarding the alleged violation(s). After closing its proof, the alleged violator shall then be given the opportunity to rebut the proof present or the conduct alleged to have happened.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <heading>Burden of Proof.</heading>
          <text>After the Environment Division has made its presentation and met its burden of proof based upon the preponderance of the evidence, the burden shall shift to the alleged violator to rebut the evidence and testimony.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <heading>Evidentiary Issues.</heading>
          <text>The Tribal Court is free to accept or reject any documentary evidence</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <heading>Judgment.</heading>
          <text>After hearing all of the testimony, the Court shall issue a written decision to the parties within thirty (30) days of the hearing. If the Court finds in favor of the Environment Division it may issue a civil fine of up to <strong>ten thousand ($10,000.00) dollars, except for an Open Dump violation which shall be assessed a fine of five hundred ($500.00) dollars for zero (0) to one (1) ton of Solid Waste and five hundred ($500.00) dollars per ton for any Solid Waste above one (1) ton.</strong> In addition to the civil fine the Court can include any cost for the remediation needed to remedy the violation and any other relief provided by law, including the assessment and recovery of civil penalties and clean up and administrative costs associated with the enforcement of <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite>. If the Court determines that the Environment Division failed to meet its burden it shall dismiss the complaint. Any fines collected shall be remitted to the Tribal General Fund and divided between the Compliance Department and Environment Division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <heading>Failure to satisfy Judgment.</heading>
          <text>After issuing a judgment, if it is not satisfied within thirty (30) days then the respondent's name may be transferred to Tribal Council or its designee who may issue a reminder notice to the judgment debtor. Failure to remit payment after receiving such a notice may prompt the Compliance Department to issue a "Delinquency Letter" to the Court with a copy provided to the judgment debtor notifying the Tribal Court the judgment debtor has not yet complied. Once received, the Court Clerk shall issue a "letter of warning" to the judgment debtor. The letter of warning must state that further non-compliance may result in a judgment for contempt of Court and that the enforcement of the judgment may result in measurements such as garnishment of wages and the revocation of tribal licenses. If the judgment is not satisfied within ten (10) days from the date the letter is sent by the Court Clerk, the Compliance Department shall notify the Court. The Court shall set a hearing that must take place no later than ten (10) days from the date of notification by the Compliance Department. At the hearing, the Compliance Department may enter evidence demonstrating that the judgment debtor has not satisfied his/her judgment. The judgment debtor/respondent may appear and offer evidence. After review of the evidence, the Court may enter an enforcement order revoking any Tribal licenses or garnish the judgment debtor's wages. The Tribal licenses and/or Tribal services shall remain suspended until the judgment has been paid and proof of payment has been made to the Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>
          <strong>APPEALS</strong>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Within thirty (30) days of the judgment, a respondent may file an appeal with the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Court of Appeals. The appeal shall be limited to the fine and penalty imposed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-02-26" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-09" eff="2020-02-26" path="attachments|law|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.04</num>
    <heading>Pesticide Regulation</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.010</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe (The "Tribe"), is responsible for the health, safety, education and welfare of all community members. With respect to pesticide usage it has the authority, responsibility and jurisdiction to exercise sovereign rights in governing pesticide usage on the Saint Regis Mohawk Reservation (Reservation). Through its Environment Division, the Tribe has determined that the management of pesticides through Tribal regulation will ensure the protection of Tribal member health by reducing unnecessary health risk exposures to pesticides.</text>
      <text>Further, the EPA's regulations under Environmental Protection Acts, Title 40 of the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) Part 171 provide that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>An Indian tribe may develop its own plan for certifying private and commercial applicators to use or supervise the use of Restricted Use Pesticides (RUPS), subject to the approval of EPA;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>If a tribe does not develop its own certification plan, the tribe may choose to utilize a state's certification program, with the concurrence of that state, subject to the approval of EPA; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>EPA can implement a federal plan for the certification of applicators of RUPS where no other EPA-approved state or tribal applicator certification plan is in effect.</text>
      </para>
      <text>The Tribe's strategy for regulating pesticide usage within its jurisdiction is to exercise option 3, relying upon EPA to certify RUP applicators. Additionally, the Tribe will exercise its sovereign right to regulate the use of General Use Pesticides (GUPS) within its jurisdiction through this regulation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|1.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.020</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <text>The authority of the Tribe to enact the Pesticide Regulation lies in the inherent sovereign authority of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe the Tribal Procedures Act section IV (C) (1), (2), (10) and (13) (TCR 2013-32); and the Tribal Court and Judiciary Code Section V and VI (TCR 2008- 22).</text>
      <text>Tribes cannot be granted primacy status under FIFRA. The EPA, however, does permit cooperative agreements to tribes who cooperate with EPA for the enforcement of FIFRA and who have developed their own Tribal Codes for pesticide use on tribal lands. If a tribal inspector uses tribal credentials for an inspection, enforcement can be pursued by the Tribal Council. If EPA credentials are used for an inspection, the Tribe shall send the inspection file and all information to the EPA's regional office.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|2.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.030</num>
      <heading>Federal Certification Rule</heading>
      <text>Under the authority of Section 11(a)(1) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, Rodenticide, Act (FIFRA), and in accordance with the regulations found at Title 40 of the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) Section 171.11, the EPA is implementing a federal pesticide applicator certification plan (EPA plan) for those areas of Indian country where no other EPA-approved or EPA-implemented plan applies. This EPA plan describes a program for the certification of applicators of restricted use pesticides (RUPS) in Indian country based on the certification requirements enumerated at 40 CFR Part 171.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes">Consistent with the statutory definition of Indian country, as well as federal case law interpreting this statutory language, EPA treats lands held by the federal government in trust for Indian tribes that exist outside of formal reservations as informal reservations, and thus as Indian country.</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes"><em>Indian country</em>: As defined at 18 USC ยง 1151: "(a) all land within the limits of any Indian reservation under the jurisdiction of the United States Government, notwithstanding the issuance of any patent, and, including rights-of-way running through the reservation; (b) all dependent Indian communities within the borders of the United States whether within the original or subsequently acquired territory thereof, and whether within or without the limits of a state; and (c) all Indian allotments, the Indian titles to which have not been extinguished, including rights-of-way running through the same."</annotation>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|2.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.040</num>
      <heading>Terms and Definitions</heading>
      <text><strong>Applicator</strong> - A person who uses a pesticide for the purpose of preventing, repelling or mitigating any pest as defined under this regulation.</text>
      <text><strong>Pesticide</strong> - A substance or mixture of substances intended for preventing, destroying, repelling or mitigating any pest as defined under the FIFRA (7 USC 136-136y).</text>
      <text><strong>Certification</strong> - The processes that are administered by the Tribe, EPA or a State which confirms that the qualifications and credentials of a pesticide applicator meet applicable, Tribal, Federal or State requirements in order to be accredited.</text>
      <text><strong>Certified Applicator</strong> - The term "certified applicator" means any individual who is certified under FIFRA section 11 as authorized to use or supervise the use of any pesticide which is classified for restricted use. Any applicator who holds or applies registered pesticides, or uses dilutions of registered pesticides consistent with subsection (ee), only to provide a service of controlling pests without delivering any unapplied pesticide to any person so served is not deemed to be a seller or distributor of pesticides under FIFRA.</text>
      <text><strong>Commercial Applicator</strong> - The term "commercial applicator" means an applicator who uses or supervises the use of any pesticide which is classified for restricted use for any purpose or on any property other than as provided by the definition of Private Applicator.</text>
      <text><strong>EPA Plan</strong> - The US EPA federal certification requirements for applicators or restricted use pesticides (RUPs) in Indian Country under the authority of Section 11(a) (1) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (FIFRA), and in accordance with the regulations found at Title 40 of the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) Section 171.11</text>
      <text><strong>General Use Pesticide (GUP)</strong> - Any pesticide which has not been classified as Restricted Use. A pesticide that that will not ordinarily cause unreasonable adverse effects on the user or on the environment when used in accordance with their label instructions. These are available to the public.</text>
      <text><strong>Indian Country</strong> - All land within the limits of an Indian reservation as defined by 18 USC ยง 1151.</text>
      <text><strong>Labeling</strong> - All labels and all other written, printed, or graphic matter: (a) accompanying the pesticide or device at any time; or (b) to which reference is made on the label or in literature accompanying the pesticide or device, except to current official publications of the Environmental Protection Agency, the United States Departments of Agriculture and Interior, and the Department of Health and Human Services, State experiment stations, State agricultural colleges, and other similar Federal or State institutions or agencies authorized by law to conduct research in the field of pesticides.</text>
      <text><strong>Label(s)</strong> - The written, printed, or graphic matter on, or attached to, the pesticide or device or any of its containers or wrappers.</text>
      <text><strong>Pesticide Incident</strong> - Any exposure or effect from a pesticide's use that is not expected or intended. Pesticide incidents may involve humans, wildlife, plants, domestic animals (e.g. pets) and bees.</text>
      <text><strong>Pesticide Registry Number</strong> - The EPA issued number that corresponds to an EPA registered pesticide. The EPA Registered Number of a product for primary registrants consists of two sets of numbers separated by a hyphen. The first set of numbers refers to the registrant's company identification number, and the second set of numbers represents the product number.</text>
      <text><strong>Private Applicator</strong> - The term "private applicator" means a certified applicator who uses or supervises the use of any pesticide which is classified for restricted use for purposes of producing any agricultural commodity on property owned or rented by the applicator or the applicator's employer or (if applied without compensation other than trading of personal services between producers of agricultural commodities) on the property of another person as defined by FIFRA.</text>
      <text>A private applicator is a farmer, rancher, orchardist, nursery producer, greenhouse operator, etc. who uses or supervises the use of restricted use pesticides to produce an agricultural commodity on property owned or rented by the applicator or his/her employer or (if applied without compensation other than trading of personal services between producers or agricultural commodities) on the property of another person.</text>
      <text><strong>Restricted Use Pesticide (RUP)</strong> - Under FIFRA, pesticides (or the particular use or uses of a pesticide) that may generally cause, without additional regulatory restrictions, unreasonable adverse effects on the environment, including injury to the applicator. A pesticide that only certified pesticide applicators or those under the supervision of a certified applicator may use.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|3.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.050</num>
      <heading>Registration Requirements</heading>
      <text>All Applicators shall be registered through the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe's Compliance Department in order to be able to apply pesticides within the jurisdiction of the Tribe before operating on the territory. Pesticide applicators shall also meet any and all other provisions of Tribal regulatory requirements, including but not limited, to business licenses or permits, Tribal good standing policy requirements, etc.</text>
      <text>Any person who applies restricted use pesticides in an area the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe covered by the EPA plan will need a federal certificate from EPA.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.060</num>
      <heading>Permits</heading>
      <text>Applicators shall be issued a Tribal permit that is valid for one (1) year. Each permit is effective Tsiothohrkรณ:wa/January 1 to Tsiothรณhrha/December 31, each year.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.070</num>
      <heading>RUP/GUP</heading>
      <text>All Applicators that hold certifications in other jurisdictions outside of the Reservation shall also be currently registered with its respective jurisdiction and the EPA, and currently be in compliance with the pesticide regulations of those jurisdictions and Applicators shall verify its standing by presenting copies of certifications and licenses held in their pertinent state and by the EPA.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.080</num>
      <heading>GUP</heading>
      <text>Applicators may obtain permits to apply GUP within the jurisdiction of the Tribe. The GUP Permit is only issued to on-territory Applicators and restricts the use of pesticides to GUPS only. This type of permit is only valid for the Reservation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.090</num>
      <heading>Applications</heading>
      <text>All Applicators shall complete and submit a Tribal Applicator Permit Application for Pesticide Applicator Certification.</text>
      <text>The permit shall be submitted to the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, Attention: Tribal Compliance Office, 71 Margaret Terrance Memorial Way, Akwesasne, NY 13655.</text>
      <text>Once approved a Tribal Applicator Photo-ID permit card that will be issued. The Applicator shall be required to remit payment of $120.00 to the Tribe's Accounting Department.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.100</num>
      <heading>Permit Fees</heading>
      <text>The fee for an annual permit shall be no less than $120 for a permit. The Tribe reserves the right to increase permit fees to meet administrative costs but shall notify applicators in writing in advance of fee rate increases. The fee includes the cost of a Tribal Photo-ID Permit.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|4.5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.110</num>
      <heading>Reporting Requirements</heading>
      <text>As a condition of either permit the Tribally certified Applicators shall be required to submit annual reports no later than thirty (30) days from Tsiothรณhrha/December 31 of each year (Applicators may submit reports more frequently). Failure to submit an annual report will result in suspension of a Tribal certification.</text>
      <text>The content of the annual report shall include:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Applicator Name (First, Last, M.I.)</li>
          <li>Applicator physical address</li>
          <li>Applicator mailing address</li>
          <li>Applicator phone number(s)</li>
          <li>Tribal Permit Number, Federal Certification Number, State Certification Number</li>
          <li>Sales and Usage Report</li>
          <li>List names of all pesticides used within the jurisdiction of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe</li>
          <li>List the quantities (U.S. liquid measures for liquid materials and U.S. dry weight measures for all dry materials) of all pesticides used within the jurisdiction of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|5.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.120</num>
      <heading>Accidental Releases</heading>
      <text>In the event of an accidental release of a pesticide, where there is an imminent threat to human health and the environment, Applicators are required to immediately contact the Tribe's Environmental Response Team, 518-358-5937 during regular business hours or the Tribe's Police Department, 518-358-9200, after regular business hours.</text>
      <text>Any accidental pesticide release is reportable if:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>There is an impact to human health</li>
          <li>There is an impact to the environment, including a threat or spill into a sanitary sewer, storm sewer and/or surface water or ground water</li>
          <li>There is a fire, explosion or safety hazard</li>
          <li>The spill has not immediately been cleaned up</li>
          <li>The spill was more than the reportable quantity under Federal Law</li>
          <li>A spill involving the commercial transport of a pesticide as governed by the US Department of Transportation</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <text>Applicators may be subject to reportable quantities under additional regulatory requirements including but not limited to the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act (CERCLA), 42 USC 9601, the Federal Water Pollution Control Act, 33 USC 1321(b)(2)(A) and 1317 (a), section 3001 of the Solid Waste Disposal Act, 42 USC 6921, Section 112 of the Clean Air Act, 42 U.S.C 7412. It is the responsibility of Applicators to know and understand the regulations to which they are subject.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|6.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.130</num>
      <heading>Pesticide Incidents</heading>
      <text>Applicators are required to report any pesticide incidents to the Tribe's Compliance and Environmental Office, providing the Applicators name, address, phone number, e-mail, date, location, time of day, pesticide name and EPA registry number and nature of incident (human exposure or illness, animal exposure or illness (pets or livestock), pesticide drift, wildlife incident (wildlife, bees, soil or water), problems with a pesticide container or label. A Pesticide Incident Report will consist of:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A verbal report, made in person or by phone to the Tribe's Compliance and Environmental Office at the time of the incident or as soon as possible upon discovery an incident and,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Filing of a written report immediately after, but no later than 24-hours, after filing a verbal report</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>If the incident occurs on a weekend or holiday the applicator is required to file a report by the next business day of operation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|6.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.140</num>
      <heading>Enforcement</heading>
      <text>Any violation of the Tribal Pesticide regulation may result in the revocation of an Applicator's permit, institution of fines and penalties as determined by a Tribal Compliance Office official, seizure of materials for evidence, and restitution for damages or losses that may have resulted from violations of this Ordinance. Additionally, the Tribe will advise EPA of any violations.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|7.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.150</num>
      <heading>Enforcement Actions</heading>
      <text>Enforcement Policy: It is the policy of the Tribe to encourage informal, practical, result- oriented resolution of alleged violations and actions needed to prevent damage to Saint Regis Mohawk Indian Reservation resources or harm to the health, safety or welfare of the Reservation population. It is also the policy of the Tribe, consistent with the principles of due process, to provide effective procedures for enforcement.</text>
      <text>Enforcement Agency: The Tribe's Environment Compliance Officer ("Officer") shall be responsible for enforcing the provisions of this Code. Specifically, the Officer shall conduct investigations when a complaint is received by the Tribal Compliance Office, Environment Division or other Tribal agency believes that a violation of this Ordinance has occurred.</text>
      <text>Enforcement Activities: Where a verified complaint shall be filed with the Tribe and reviewed by the Environmental Compliance Officer alleging that, or where the Tribe itself shall have cause to believe that, any person is violating any pesticide regulation or permit condition, the Environmental Compliance Officer shall cause a prompt investigation to be made.</text>
      <text>Notice of Violation: Cease and Desist Order: If the Officer finds after an investigation pursuant to this Code that a violation of any regulation or permit condition exists, the Officer shall promptly notify both the alleged violator and the Tribal Council in writing. In the case of an apparent violation of this Ordinance, the Officer is authorized to issue a Notice of Violation to the person(s) apparently responsible for the violation, and, if the apparent violation occurred on property owned by a person other than the alleged violator, a Notice of Violation shall also be issued to the landowner.</text>
      <text>In the case of a continuing violation or a threatened violation, the Tribal Council shall issue a Cease and Desist Order to prevent the violation from continuing or occurring.</text>
      <text>Failure to comply with a Cease and Desist Order shall constitute a Second violation of this Ordinance. Both a Notice of Violation and a Cease and Desist Order may be issued for a single incident. A Notice of Violation will include a request to appear before the Officer at an enforcement hearing at a specified time and date, and shall advise the alleged violator that failure to appear may result in the imposition of civil penalties.</text>
      <text>If an Immediate Cease and Desist Order is issued without an accompanying Notice of Violation, the Order will inform the recipient that failure to comply with the Order will constitute a violation of this Ordinance, which will result in the issuance of a Notice of Violation that will indicate the alleged violations of this ordinance and may result in the imposition of civil penalties.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|7.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.160</num>
      <heading>Hearings on Violations</heading>
      <text>Informal/Formal Hearings: The Officer shall afford the landowner or his or her representative reasonable opportunities to discuss proposed enforcement actions at an informal or formal hearing prior to taking further enforcement action, unless the Officer determines that there may be either imminent environmental damage to a Reservation resource or adverse impact upon the health, safety and welfare of the Reservation population. Informal or formal hearings may be used at any stage in the enforcement proceedings, except that the Officer may refuse to conduct informal or formal hearings with respect to any matter then pending before the Officer.</text>
      <text>Reports Required: The Officer shall keep written notes of the date and place of the hearing, the persons in attendance, the subject matter discussed and any decisions reached with respect to further enforcement action.</text>
      <text>Enforcement Hearings: If the landowner and the Officer are unable to resolve the matter via an informal or formal hearing, the Officer is authorized to conduct adjudicatory hearings to determine if a violation of this Code has occurred. In such a hearing the person so charged shall be entitled, at his or her own expense, to be represented by an attorney or other representative. The Officer shall rule that a violation of this Ordinance has occurred if it finds that the charges are supported by a preponderance of the credible evidence, which supports a finding that a violation occurred.</text>
      <text>Within thirty (30) days after the date of any enforcement hearing, the Officer shall issue a written decision. If the Officer determines that a violation has occurred and that the person(s) charged was (were) responsible for the violation, the Officer's decision shall include an Enforcement Order.</text>
      <text>Civil Penalties and Corrective Action: An Enforcement Order shall direct any person(s) found to have committed a violation of this Ordinance to take whatever corrective action the Officer deems appropriate under the circumstances. An Enforcement Order may impose civil penalties in accordance with a schedule of civil penalties prescribed under these rules. Alternatively, an Enforcement Order may impose civil penalties in the event that a person found to have committed a violation of this Code does not take corrective action in accordance with the Order within a prescribed time frame. If a person who has been found to have committed a violation does not take corrective action within the prescribed time frame, an appropriate department or agency of the Tribal government may take the necessary corrective action, in which case the amount of any civil penalty shall be increased by twice the amount of the cost incurred by the Tribal department or agency in taking the corrective action.</text>
      <text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Ordinance, if the Officer determines that noncompliance with this Ordinance is presenting an imminent and substantial threat to the public health, welfare or environment and determines, in consultation with the Tribe's attorneys, that it is not practicable to assure prompt protection of the public health, welfare or environment of an administrative or judicial enforcement action under this part, the Officer may issue such orders as may be necessary to protect the public health, welfare or environment. Any such order shall be effective immediately upon issuance and shall remain in effect for a period not to exceed sixty (60) days. Revocation of Permit. Failure of any person to comply with any Enforcement Orders shall result in an immediate revocation of his or her permit. In order to obtain a reinstatement of such permit, the person(s) against whom the Enforcement Order was issued must first demonstrate compliance with the Order and pay all outstanding penalties and then petition for reinstatement of the permit with the name of the particular Tribal Agency].</text>
      <text>Special Provisions for Tribal Departments and Agencies: In any case in which any Tribal agency or department is alleged to have violated the terms and conditions of a pesticide permit, or to have conducted activities without a permit, the Compliance Department shall bring the matter to the attention of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, Tribal Council who shall consider taking action to ensure compliance with this Ordinance. If the matter cannot be resolved informally, the particular Tribal Agency shall conduct an enforcement hearing for the purpose of making factual determinations and issuing a decision recommending a course of corrective action if necessary.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|7.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.170</num>
      <heading>Appeals</heading>
      <text>Once the Compliance Officer has issued a decision any person who is aggrieved by the decision has the right to appeal through the Tribal Appellate Court. This appeal must be filed in writing as a notice of appeal to the Tribal Appellate Court.</text>
      <text>Any person who is aggrieved by the issuance or denial of an applicator permit without respect to whether that person, corporation or other entity is a party to such permit application, or who is the subject of an Enforcement Order, may file an appeal with the Tribal Appellate Court. The Tribal Appellate Court is authorized to hear such appeals.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|8.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.180</num>
      <heading>Certification</heading>
      <text>A person becomes a certified applicator through meeting the requirements of the Tribe and, the EPA and by his/her pertinent state.</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Persons applying GUP commercially as defined under this ordinance, are required to be certified by the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, and</li>
          <li>Persons are required to be Federally Certified by EPA to be able to apply RUP on Tribal lands and must also obtain a Tribal permit, and</li>
          <li>Persons are required to be certified by their pertinent state to be able to apply pesticides on Tribal lands</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|9.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.190</num>
      <heading>Training Requirements for Gup Permits</heading>
      <text>Applicators who apply GUPS only must have successfully completed a basic pesticide core training program that includes the following material:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Pests</li>
          <li>Pesticides</li>
          <li>Formulations</li>
          <li>Pesticide Exposure and Risks</li>
          <li>The Toxicity of Pesticides</li>
          <li>Protecting Yourself</li>
          <li>Responding to a Pesticide Exposure</li>
          <li>Ecology and Environmental Considerations</li>
          <li>Proper Pesticide Disposal</li>
          <li>Pesticide Storage</li>
          <li>Safety Precautions with Pesticides</li>
          <li>Personal Protection for the Applicator and Worker</li>
          <li>Protecting Water from Pesticide Pollution</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <text>Applicators must maintain their competencies by completing a minimum of three (3) Continuing Education Units (CEU's) a year in a pesticide related training course. Certificates of completion must be submitted with permit applications/renewals to verify course work.</text>
      <text>Applicators who apply RUPs must meet the training requirements of their respective state certification program. A current applicator's state certification upon application or renewal must be present with a permit application/renewal.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|10.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.200</num>
      <heading>Right to Know</heading>
      <text>Employers within the jurisdiction of the Tribe will be required to inform employees about the use of pesticides used in the workplace. The process for providing information consists of:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Providing a list of all pesticides used in the workplace</li>
          <li>Access to Safety Data Sheets and container labels</li>
          <li>Making proper notification of the planned use of pesticides in workplace with 48-hours advanced notice</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|11.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.210</num>
      <heading>Notification</heading>
      <text>Pesticide Applicators are required to provide notice of all pesticide use including all indoor and outdoor applications made in public and commercial buildings and for agricultural applications. Notification shall consist of posting signs on the property to be treated a minimum of 48-hours before application treatment and remain posted on the property a minimum of 24-hours after application. However, certain products may have labels with stricter notification requirements. In these particular instances the label directions must be followed.</text>
      <text>Notification signage shall display the following information:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Indication that pesticides will be applied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The date of application.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Date the notice is given.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Date the notice expires, maximum of seven days.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Name and telephone number of a person who can give information about what was applied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>EPA Registration number and full name of pesticide (product common name).</text>
      </para>
      <text>Signage specifications are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text><strong>Size</strong> - A minimum of one-foot by one-foot in dimension.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text><strong>Color</strong> - Dark lettering on a yellow background.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text><strong>Location</strong> - Posted in a conspicuous place along the principal street frontage of the property to be sprayed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text><strong>Posted</strong> - At common access points of commercial buildings or apartment complexes.</text>
      </para>
      <text>Private homeowners using pesticides in their own home and on their own property are not required to comply with notification requirements.</text>
      <text>In addition to public posting, the applicator shall make written notification to the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, Environment Division of plans to apply pesticides. The Applicator is required to notify the Tribe a minimum of 48-hours in advance of an application. However, certain products may have labels with stricter notification requirements. In these particular instances the label directions must be followed.</text>
      <text>Information to be provided to the Environment Division in the written notification shall consist of:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Date or dates of pesticide use</li>
          <li>Full name of pesticide(s) product(s)</li>
          <li>The pest(s) to be treated</li>
          <li>Where the pesticide(s) will be applied</li>
          <li>Re-entry period restrictions (if any)</li>
          <li>The name of the pesticide Applicator (individual) and Company Name</li>
          <li>Applicator registration number</li>
          <li>Pest controller contact number(s)</li>
          <li>EPA Registration number and full name of pesticide (product common name)</li>
          <li>Where pesticide will be applied within a building or site</li>
          <li>E-mail address of applicator</li>
          <li>Applicator certification number</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|11.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.220</num>
      <heading>Exemptions</heading>
      <text>The Tribe exempts Minimum risk pesticides and Low Impact Pesticides from the notification requirements. Refer to https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticide for guidelines on minimum risk pesticides. Low impact pesticides in general are antimicrobial products and disinfectants, see <cite path="5.04|A">Appendix A</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|12.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.230</num>
      <heading>Amendments</heading>
      <text>Amendments to this this Ordinance must be initiated in accordance with provisions of Tribal procedures for adopting Tribal laws and ordinances. The amendment and supporting documentation must be submitted in writing.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|13.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.240</num>
      <heading>Repeal</heading>
      <text>Repeal to this Ordinance must be initiated in accordance with provisions of Tribal procedures for adopting Tribal laws and ordinances. The repeal and supporting documentation must be submitted in writing.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|14.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.250</num>
      <heading>Severability</heading>
      <text>In the event that any provision of this Ordinance shall be found or declared to be invalid, the remaining provisions of this ordinance shall be unaffected thereby, and shall remain in full force and effect.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|15.0" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <container>
      <prefix>APPENDIX</prefix>
      <num>A</num>
      <heading>LOW IMPACT PESTICIDES</heading>
      <text>The following ingredients or types of pesticides are also considered low impact.</text>
      <para>
        <num>a.</num>
        <text>Formulation Types - gels, pastes, or baits. Ant traps and insecticide gels are good examples of this class of low impact pesticides. Rodent baits also fit into this designation, although rodent baits should be rare.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>b.</num>
        <text>Antimicrobial products - pesticides used to kill microorganisms such as bacteria and fungus. Disinfectants, cleaners, mold and mildew removers all fall into this classification.</text>
        <text>"Antimicrobial agents" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Disinfectants intended to destroy or irreversibly inactivate infectious or other undesirable bacteria, pathogenic fungi, or viruses on surfaces or inanimate objects;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Sanitizers intended to reduce the number of living bacteria or viable virus particles on inanimate surfaces, in water, or in air;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Bacteriostats intended to inhibit the growth of bacteria in the presence of moisture;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Sterilizers intended to destroy viruses and all living bacteria, fungi, and their spores, on inanimate surfaces; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Fungicides and fungistats intended to inhibit the growth of, or destroy fungi (including yeasts) pathogenic to man or other animals on inanimate surfaces;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Commodity preservatives and protectants intended to inhibit the growth of, or destroy bacteria in or on raw materials (such as adhesives or plastics) used in manufacturing, or manufactured products (such as fuel, textiles, lubricants, and paints); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>General use algaecides labeled for use in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Swimming pools, hot tubs, whirlpools, spas, ornamental ponds, fountains, fish tanks, and waterbeds;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>ii.</num>
            <text>Water, wastewater and sewerage treatment plants, but only where there is a controlled inlet and outlet; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>iii.</num>
            <text>Industrial, commercial, and manufacturing processes.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>c.</num>
        <text>Specific Active Ingredients - Specific pesticide ingredients added to the low impact designation are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>boric acid</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>disodium octoborate tetrahydrate</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>silica gel</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>diatomaceous earth</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>d.</num>
        <text>Microbe based insecticides - the most common example of this would be bacillus thuringiensis or "Bt", a widely used microbe that is the ingredient in many home and garden products, mosquito larvicides, and gypsy moth control products.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>e.</num>
        <text>Botanical insecticides (not synthetic) - a common example of this would be pyrethrins, extracted from the chrysanthemum plant, or neem oil that is extracted from kernels of the neem plant. Synthetic versions of botanicals or those that contain chemical synergists to enhance the potency do not qualify as low impact.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>f.</num>
        <text>Biological, living control agents- a common example of this would be a pesticide that uses parasitic nematodes (a small worm-like organism) as its active ingredient. These nematodes are used to control a wide variety of insects. Beneficial insects would be another type of control agent that would fit into this category.</text>
      </para>
      <annotation app="2020-01-08" doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2020-01" eff="2020-01-08" path="attachments|law|A" type="History"/>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
