<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe Res. No. 2007-63" codify:doc="Saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Code of Law">
  <num>2007-63</num>
  <heading>Tribal Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership Determinations</heading>
  <meta>
    <stub/>
    <effective>2007-07-19</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2007-07-19</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/2007-63.pdf">Res. No. 2007-63</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Council is the duly recognized governing body of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe and is responsible for promoting the health, safety, education and general welfare of all community members; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the authority and responsibility to determine all matters of Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership of the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe is wholly vested with the Tribal Council; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the responsibility to administrate and record Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership determinations of the Tribal Council are vested with the Tribal Clerk; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>in accordance with Tribal Council Resolution # 2005-90 (Tribal Membership Board and Membership Code) it is hereby further ratified that proof of a minimum of twenty five percent (25%) Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum shall be required for Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership with the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED THAT,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council hereby directs that all determinations of Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum and the requisite twenty five percent (25%) Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum for purposes of Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership be completed in accordance with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text><em>Unless there is a reasonable basis to determine otherwise</em>, all great-grandparents listed as Saint Regis Mohawk (fourth generation) of an applicant shall be deemed 100% Saint Regis Mohawk <u>if</u>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>they are presently enrolled Saint Regis Mohawk tribal members or were enrolled Saint Regis Mohawk tribal members at the time of their death, or;</strong>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>if their names appeared on any applicable/official Saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Census Rolls, or;</strong>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>the last names of one or either of the applicants' great grandparents are names that are readily recognizable as being Saint Regis Mohawk.</heading>
        </para>
        <text>If none of the above requirement can be fulfilled then there shall be a reasonable basis for additional research to be conducted to determine whether or not the great grandparents (fourth generation) can be identified as Saint Regis Mohawk or not. Such research may include conducting a review of the applicant's family history beyond the fourth generation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>II.</num>
        <text>For purposes of calculating Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum and in order to determine whether an applicant has fulfilled the requisite twenty five percent (25%) blood quantum required for Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership with the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe, the Tribal Clerk shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>determine the Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum of each parent of applicant in accordance with the above, and;</strong>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>divide the Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum of each parent by one-half (1/2), and;</strong>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <heading>combine/add the Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum Of each parent to determine the Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum of applicant.</heading>
        </para>
        <text>Determinations of Saint Regis Mohawk blood quantum may result in an amount that is less than the requisite twenty five percent (25%) necessary for Eligibility, Enrollment and Membership with the Saint Regis Mohawk Tribe. Notwithstanding this fact, an individual whose blood quantum is below the requisite twenty five percent (25%) may still use such amount to calculate the eligibility of that individual's biological children, if applicable.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>Saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Council</text>
    <text>
      <table class="layout-table">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>_____________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">_____________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">_____________________</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Chief James W. Ransom</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">Chief Margaret Terrance</td>
            <td class="text-indent-2">Chief Barbara A. Lazore</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text><strong>CERTIFICATION</strong>: <em>This is to certify that the saint Regis Mohawk Tribal Council, pursuant to the authority vested therein, duly passed the above resolution.</em></text>
    <text>
      <table class="layout-table">
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>___________________________________</td>
            <td class="text-indent-4">July 19, 2007</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Patricia Thomas, Tribal Clerk</td>
            <td class="text-indent-4">Date</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
